A variable is a tensor whose value is
変数はテンソルで 値は初期化され
initialized and then the value gets changed as a program runs.
プログラムの実行時に 変更されます
Let's take a close look at this example.
この例を詳しく見てみましょう
I have a function called forward pass,
forward_passという関数があります
which takes two parameters,
パラメータw、xを受け入れて
w and x, and multiplies them.
それらを掛け合わせます
Well, it's a matrix multiply because these are tensors,
これらはテンソルのため
but it multiplies w and x.
行列乗算になります
In my train loop function,
train_loop関数では
I basically create the tensor w except
テンソルwを作成します
that w is not a constant like the tensors that we've been looking at so far.
このwは これまでのような 定数ではなく
W is a variable.
変数です
It has a name, weights.
weightsという名前が付き
Its shape is 1,2,
形状は1, 2です
which means that it has one row and two columns.
これは1行2列 つまり
It's a 1 by 2 matrix.
1x2行列です
And when w is initialized,
ここではwを初期化しません
we are not initializing it here because remember,
TensorFlowは
TensorFlow is a lazy evaluation framework and so we are only building the graph.
遅延評価フレームワークなので グラフを作成するだけです
We're not yet running it.
まだ実行しません
When w is initialized,
wの初期化には
it will be initialized by a truncated normal initializer.
「truncated_normal_initializer」 を使用します
Now this is a very common initializer that
一般的なイニシャライザで
It initializes a variable to random numbers,
変数を初期化して 乱数にします
but these random numbers are not uniformly distributed.
均一に分散せず ガウス正規分布で
Instead, they have a Gaussian normal distribution with zero mean and unit variants.
ゼロ平均と単位分散を 使用します
It's very unlikely but it could happen.
可能性は低いですが あり得ます
So, what a truncated normal does, well,
truncated_normalは シグマの和乗算の
Finally, we say that the variable w is trainable.
変数wは トレーニングできます
A trainable variable is a variable that can be changed during training.
つまり トレーニング中に 変更できる変数です
The point of a variable of course is to be able to
変数は 変わるものですので
change it so most variables will be trainable.
大半はトレーニング可能です
But every once in a while,
これについては
model size reduction and then we talk about transferred learning.
モデルサイズの削減や 移転学習で紹介します
Every once in a while,
これはときどき
it can be helpful to freeze a graph to make it such that the variables are in changed.
グラフを静止させて変数を 固定するのに役立ちます
This Boolean flag lets us do that.
Booleanフラグで それを行えます
Notice that I'm calling tf.get_variable to create w. Now,
tf.get_variableを呼び出して wを作成している点に注目してください
Calling the constructor directly is not recommended.
こうした直接の呼び出しは おすすめしません
Use tf.get_variable because, as we'll see in course 9,
コース9で学ぶように tf.get_variableを使用します
it can be helpful to be able to reuse variables or create them
この場合は状況に応じて 変数を再利用したり
So, I recommend that you get into the habit of using tf.get_variable.
tf.get_variableに 慣れておくとよいでしょう
So, we then run the forward pass
次にforward_passを5回実行し
five times and store the result of the matrix multiply at each iteration.
反復ごとに 行列乗算の結果を保存します
So, after we do the product, we change the weight.
乗算を行った後 weightsを変更します
Here we are adding 0.1 to it.
ここでは 0.1を加えます
This is like a gradient update.
勾配更新のようなものです
In reality, of course,
実際には
in gradient update, we will choose what weights to change and how to change them.
変更するweightsと その方法を選択します
But here, for just demo purposes,
ここではデモが目的ですから
I'll just add 0.1 to the weights each time.
毎回 0.1を加えます
Now, from the session,
セッションから
we call train loop by passing in x.
xを渡すことで train_loopを呼び出します
The x is a 2 by 3 matrix.
xは[2, 3]行列です
So in the forward pass,
forward_passでは
we multiply w by this x. W is a 1 by 2 matrix.
[1, 2]行列のwに このxを掛けます
Multiplying a 1 by 2 by 2 by 3 gives us a 1 by 3 matrix.
[1, 2]に[2, 3]を掛けることで [1, 3]行列が得られます
So, at this point, the graph is done but we still need initialize the variables.
これでグラフは完了ですが 変数を初期化する必要があります
But that's the run stage.
ただし 通常は
We typically just initialized all the variables in
global_variables_initializerを実行して
the graph all at once by running the global variables initializer.
グラフ内の変数を 一度にすべて初期化します
So, when we now look at the value of the product after each step of the loop,
さて ループの各ステップ後の 積の値に注目すると
we notice that the 1 by 3 matrix each time is different as you would expect.
予想どおり [1, 3]行列は毎回異なります
So, let's summarize what we have just learned.
学んだことを まとめましょう
Number 1, create a variable by calling "get variable."
まずget_variableを呼び出して 変数を作成します
Well, I skipped over one line of code when I went through it, the scope piece.
今回はコードを1行飛ばしました
When you create a variable,
変数を作成するときは
you can specify the scope.
スコープを指定できます
That's where I'm telling TensorFlow to reuse the variable
毎回 新しい変数を作成するのではなく
each time instead of creating a new variable each time.
再利用するようにします
I'm calling train loop only once so it doesn't matter here,
ここでは train_loopを一度だけ呼び出すので 重要ではないものの
but if I were to call train loop again,
train_loopを再び呼び出すと
the weights would resume from where they left off.
weightsが前回の終わりから 再開します
We will create a new variable. We would reuse it.
これが変数の作成と再利用です
So, second thing that you're learning here is that when you create a variable,
学んだ2つの目の点は 変数の作成時に
you have to decide on how to initialize a variable.
初期化の方法を 決めることです
In neural network training,
ニューラルネットワーク トレーニングでは通常
Number 3, use the variable just like any other tensor when building the graph.
3番目の点は
Number 4, in your session,
4番目の点は
remember to initialize the variable.
変数を初期化することです
Usually, you will initialize all the variables
通常は global_variables_initializerを 呼び出して
together by calling the global variables initializer.
すべての変数を一緒に初期化します
And after the variables are initialized,
初期化の後
and this is point number 5,
これは5番目の点ですが
you can evaluate any tensor that you want to evaluate.
対象となるテンソルを評価します
So, in this example,
この例では
we are calling the train loop with the x,
xを使ってtrain_loopを呼び出します
but the x is a constant.
でも xは定数です
How realistic is that?
これは現実的ですか
Do you hardcode input values into your programs?
プログラムに入力値を ハードコーディングしますか
Placeholders allow you to feed in values into the graph.
プレースホルダで グラフに値をフィードできます
For example, you can read values from a text file into
たとえば 読み取った値を Pythonリストに入れ
a Python list and then feed that list into the TensorFlow graph.
TensorFlowグラフにフィードできます
So, here, a is a placeholder.
aは スカラーを保持する プレースホルダです
B is a multiplied by 4.
bはaに4を掛けたものです
If you print a, you will get the debug output of a tensor.
aを出力すると テンソルのデバッグ出力が得られます
You will learn that this particular tensor is
このテンソルは
a placeholder that expects floating point numbers to be fed into it.
浮動小数点数を受け入れる プレースホルダです
If you now want to evaluate b,
bを評価する場合
you can adjust this session.run(b).
このsession.run(b)を調整できます
You have to feed in values for the placeholders that b depends upon.
bが依存するプレースホルダ値を フィードする必要があります
So in this case,
この場合
you have to pass in a list or a numpy array of numbers for the placeholder a,
aに対してリストか 数値numpy配列を渡す必要があります
and you do this using a feed dict, a dictionary.
ここではfeed_dictを使用します
Key value pairs is what a dictionary is.
このディクショナリはKey-Valueペア
The key is a placeholder,
キーはプレースホルダで
in this case, a.
ここではaです
The value is a list of numpy array.
値はnumpy配列のリストで
And in this case, it's 1,2,3.
ここでは1,2,3です
So that's what we feed in,
これをフィードします
and so when b is evaluated,
bを評価すると
you get the value of a multiply by 4,
aに4を掛けた値を得られるため
so we get 4,8,12.
4、8、12が出力されます